THE 53RD TOSEI FESTIVAL
（第53届东成祭）
Sorry to keep you waiting!
让你们久等了
There she is.
来了
Akane, you're late!
茜，你迟到了
I'm sorry.
抱歉
I got called into a night shift suddenly at my part-time job.
昨晚我突然被叫去打工
After that, I had a report to write. I've barely slept.
回家后又赶报告，都没什么睡
Seriously?
真的假的？
Convenience stores can be tough when they're short staffed.
超商的打工也很缺人，很辛苦呢
Hey there!
喂！
Everyone!
各位！
Let's get started!
快点去逛逛吧
He's so cute!
真可爱
Just adorable!
好可爱哦
-Is that guy wearing rabbit ears -Hey!
-那个戴着兔耳 -嘿
and lost in his own world, Eita?
看起来超嗨的人是瑛太？
They're even taking photos of him.
女高中生围着他拍照耶
Eita loves festivals.
因为他超爱这种庆典活动
SO CUTE!
（好可爱）
Hey, wait!
喂，等等
Wait, you guys!
等一下！
Hey! I'm over here!
就说等我了！
COME SEE OUR COSPLAY CAFE
（欢迎来角色扮演咖啡厅）
So this is Yamada's school.
这里就是山田的学校啊
ORIGINAL STORY BY MASHIRO
（原作：Mashiro）
CREPE
（可丽饼）
There are so many booths!
有好多摊贩哦
Runa, is there anything you want to eat?
瑠奈，你有什么想吃的吗？
I don't need anything.
瑠奈不吃
Runa wants to take the entrance exam here next year.
瑠奈明年要报考这里
She's really nervous.
现在很有压力啊
Just relax, Runa!
瑠奈，放轻松
It's a chance to get used to the environment!
也许是熟悉环境的好机会哦
With my fear of failure, it's impossible.
瑠奈的精神很脆弱，没办法
TRICK ART PERFECT FOR SOCIAL MEDIA
（幻视艺术 非常适合拍照打卡）
Welcome!
欢迎光临
Whoa! Let's check that out!
我想去那里
Let's go in! I wanna!
我想进去…
Go right ahead!
路上小心
Now admitting a party of two!
两位患者入场
So where shall we go, then?
我们要去哪里逛呢？
TASTY TAKOYAKI
（美味章鱼烧）
COSPLAY CAFE
（角色扮演咖啡厅）
My stomach hurts.
肚子痛
I'm so nervous, my stomach hurts.
紧张到肚子好痛
I'm done for.
瑠奈受不了了
At this rate, I'll never be tough enough--
凭这种精神状况，考试一定也…
Okay. stop.
好了，别说了
Let's use the restroom.
我们去洗手间吧
Mr. Kamota and I just left the haunted house!
我跟鸭田先生玩完鬼屋了
Let's reconvene
大概15分钟后
in about 15 minutes.
先来会合一次吧
"Okay."
“好”，传送
That reminds me, will Yamada be able to join us?
说起来，山田有要来会合吗？
Let's ask.
问问看吧
Wait…
这…这样子
This almost makes it seem like I want to meet up with him.
显得我好像很想见他一样
Well, I guess I don't need to ask.
算了，不问也没差
I'll find out later, anyway.
反正晚点会知道，就这样吧
-That startled me! -Are you all right?
-吓我一跳 -没事吧？
They fell down!
倒下来了
Oh man…
哎呀
Is everyone okay?
没事吧？
We'll handle this.
我们来整理吧
Thank you!
谢谢
Let's bring them inside.
进教室吧
-Yamada-- -Yamada!
-山田… -山田
The freshmen are playing fighting games
一年级的格斗游戏大赛
and Yoshida from debate club took part.
教伦理的岸田有去参加
You should have seen his ridiculous moves!
他的动作超狂的
Somehow…
总觉得…
it's a little hard to interrupt.
现在不太方便叫住他
HAND IS STUCK IN MID-WAVE
（他在笑…无处可放的双手）
-Maybe he'll turn around. -Taking those inside?
-这要搬进去吗？ -他会不会转过来呢？
I'll help.
我来帮忙吧
Hey, Yamada!
喂，山田
He went inside.
走掉了
Well, it can't be helped.
算了，没办法
He looks busy.
他看起来也很忙
There's no reason he'd notice me.
不可能会注意到我吧
Give me a break…
真是的
I told them to start cleaning up the used boxes.
明明有说过先整理用完的纸箱
But they just left them there.
结果拿出去后，就放着不管
They're not the most reliable bunch.
大家做事都很随便嘛
Tsubaki,
椿同学
can I step out?
我可以稍微离开一下吗？
Sure, but…
是没关系
Where are you going?
但你要去哪里？
Not far.
有点事
This is taking a while.
好久哦
Maybe I should take a look.
我进去看看好了
Are you on your own?
你一个人吗？
Oh, you uh… noticed me?
你有…注意到我？
Yeah.
是的
I was going to call out to you,
我本来想叫你
but an accident happened.
但因为出了一点麻烦
But why are you here alone?
不过…为什么你是一个人？
Why…
为什么…
are you smiling?
你突然笑了？
Oh, no reason.
没事，没什么
Runa was with me,
瑠奈她啊
but she got nervous
好像太紧张了
and went to the bathroom.
从刚才就待在洗手间
It's been a while, so I'm a little worried.
但去了蛮久，我有点担心
I was about to go check on her.
所以正打算进去看看
It's no use.
我不行了
I'll never survive the actual exam if I'm this nervous already.
凭这样子，考试当天绝对撑不过去
You don't have a fever.
看来也没有发烧
Why don't you lie down for a while?
先躺着，观察一下状况吧
WHY AM I SUCH A COWARD…
（精神太脆弱的困扰…）
Yamada, what are you doing?
山田，你在做什么？
I'm texting Eita--
我在联络瑛太…
No!
看招
You can't!
不行！
Don't tell Eita!
你不能告诉瑛太！
He'll just make me go home!
瑠奈绝对会被带回家！
Yeah, but I can't--
就算你这么说…
I haven't had any tasty food yet,
瑠奈还没吃到好吃的
or had any fun at all!
也什么都没玩到
Doesn't your stomach hurt?
你现在胃在痛吧？
There are a whole bunch of foods I want to try!
瑠奈想在这里吃很多好吃的
To prepare, I haven't eaten anything since last night!
所以从昨晚开始就什么都没吃
Maybe that's why!
这才是原因吧
In that case, I'll go buy some things.
那我先去买回来吧
Get better soon, so you're able to eat!
希望你复原之后吃得下，好吗？
In that case…
那么…
A crepe,
可丽饼
a cheese dog,
芝士热狗
takoyaki,
章鱼烧
and lastly, I'd like to try the tonjiru soup I saw in the courtyard.
也想吃中庭卖的猪肉味噌汤
Oh, and I definitely want the commemorative festival t-shirt.
校庆限定纪念T恤也非买不可
Sure!
好好
Where do they sell the t-shirts?
哪里有在卖纪念T恤？
I'll show you.
我带你去
Come back soon!
路上小心
Are you sure you don't have to help your classmates, Yamada?
你不用回去班上帮忙吗？
-Hey, look! -Over there…
-不会吧？ -你们看
Yeah.
-她是谁啊？ -没关系
I had planned on ending my shift in the afternoon.
-我原本就预计下午离开班上 -真的假的？
Oh, I'm glad.
那就好
My work is all behind the scenes,
因为我是负责后勤
so during the event, I'm free.
在活动当天其实蛮闲的
What did your class do for the event?
你的班上是做什么？
We teamed up with the class next door and built a giant maze outside.
联合隔壁班在外面做了巨型迷宫…
Say…
话说
Everyone's looking at us, aren't they?
是不是有好多人在盯着我们？
ON PINS AND NEEDLES
（如坐针毡）
You noticed?
你注意到了？
Good.
太好了
I might get stabbed from behind.
感觉背后会遇袭
Better walk ahead of him.
我离他远一点好了
Excuse me, sir.
抱歉
Oh, well if it isn't Yamada!
什么嘛，是山田
Wandering around over here?
你在这里闲晃啊？
I've heard you're finally participating in the Mr. Academy contest.
听说你今年终于要参加校草选拔了
Couldn't escape all three years, huh?
第三年没顺利逃过吗？
Oh, and what's this? You brought a girl?
很有一套嘛，带着女生？
It always annoyed me
你这么受欢迎，却总是蛮不在乎
that you ignored the attention you get,
我以为你是个讨人厌的家伙
but I guess I had you wrong.
现在我对你改观啦，臭小子
Well, Yamada? Come on!
喂！山田！喂！
You don't look familiar.
我没看过你耶
What high school do you go to?
是哪间高中的学生？
Actually, I'm a university stu--
不，我是大学生…
An older woman?!
年纪比他大？
An older woman?
比他大？
-Now I see! -She's older?
-比他大… -原来如此
You like older women, huh?
你喜欢大姐姐啊？
Way to go!
很行嘛
You've made Sensei proud!
老师我很高兴哦
He would…
那个老师
make a good gym teacher.
很有运动社团的气质呢
He is the gym teacher.
他就是体育老师
AT A LOSS FOR WORDS
（无话可说）
Yamada!
山田学长！
Is she your girlfriend?!
那个人是你的女友吗？
How long have you been dating?
是什么时候交的？
Who is she?
她到底是谁？
You really like older women?
你喜欢比你大的吗？
Who are they?
她们是谁？
Freshmen, I think.
应该是一年级生
Judging by the color of their shoes.
从鞋子颜色看得出来
Youthful energy is amazing.
年轻真不得了
Excuse me, girls… you've got it wrong.
那个…你们误会了
You really aren't dating?
所以你们没在交往吧？
Is it true?
是真的吗？
So then, why are you together?
那你们为什么走在一起？
Yamada, tell us why!
山田学长，为什么？
Who is she?
这个人是谁？
It's a lie that you like older women, right?
你喜欢比你大的是骗人的吧
What are you doing?
你们在做什么？
We finally made it outside.
终于走出校舍大楼了
TIRED… SUBJECTED TO INTERROGATION
（没力…一路上被许多女生质问）
I'm exhausted.
感觉累翻了
TOO OLD FOR THIS…
（没力…）
Hey there!
喂！
Oh, Akito is here too.
秋斗也在啊
We bought a whole bunch of stuff!
我们买了很多哦
Runa has a stomachache, again?
听说瑠奈又胃痛了？
Huh?
奇怪？
Have you aged suddenly?
Akane，你变苍老了？
Listen to this, both of you!
你们听我说啦
You won't believe what we went through to get out here!
走到这里之前真的很夸张
I bet the students raised a fuss
想必是秋斗带着女生
because Akito brought a girl to school.
在校内掀起了热议吧
The same thing happened to Runa last year.
瑠奈去年也吃到同样的苦头
It was no joke! I could feel every eye on me!
有够扯的，超多人在看我们
The fact that I'm not his girlfriend only makes it worse.
说我不是女友，大家反而无法释怀
I'm sorry I missed it.
真想见识一下啊
I'd have loved seeing you
Akane一边破坏少女希望
destroy all their hopes.
昂首阔步的模样
That's not it! It's a misunderstanding, right?
才没有！都是误会！
Well… if you're gonna get glared at, either way…
那么…反正都会被人盯着看
Take advantage.
事已至此
Why don't you start dating for real?
你们干脆交往看看如何？
TAKE ADVANTAGE.
（事已至此）
WHY DON'T YOU START DATING FOR REAL?
（你们干脆交往看看如何？）
Right, Akito?
对吧，秋斗？
Well, I guess…
这个嘛…
you have a point.
也是
What?!
什么？
-Akane's got such a bright personality. -What are you--
-你胡说什么… -而且Akane很开朗，不错吧？
Yeah.
是啊
And you share online games as a hobby!
也爱玩在线游戏，意气相投
-You can't just-- -Yeah.
-等等，你乱凑合什么？ -是啊
A couple it is!
好啦，配对成功
Just kidding!
开玩笑啦
Akane…?
Akane…
S-Sorry!
抱…抱歉
It was just a joke!
我只是在闹着玩
I'm really sorry!
抱歉啦
I was just teasing Akito.
我只是想闹秋斗啦
Oh, a j… joke?
是闹着玩啊
Sorry!
抱歉哦
I have to go shop at the booths!
我得去买东西才行
Runa needs her lunch!
要去买瑠奈想吃的
-Akane… -Akane!
-Akane -小茜
I hate you, Eita!
我讨厌瑛太！
And don't you make fun of me either, Yamada!
山田你也不要开我玩笑！
Damn it!
气死我了！
This is bad.
糟糕
Akane got caught in the middle of my teasing Akito…
本来想闹秋斗，却害Akane出糗
You two wait here.
你们在这边等一下
I'm gonna apologize--
我去向她道歉…
In that case…
在那种情况下…
Take advantage.
事已至此
Why don't you start dating for real?
你们干脆交往看看如何？
"Yeah, yeah. Very funny."
好啦，玩笑就开到这里
That's what I should have said!
这样回答肯定才是正确答案
And yet, why…
可是…
Why did I react in that dumb way?!
我却做出那种莫名其妙的反应
Yamada…
山田他
looked really stunned.
整个人都呆住了
How humiliating!
好丢脸
RETRO CAFE
（复古咖啡厅）
Oh… I'm sorry.
抱…抱歉
STARE
（紧盯…）
Please walk slowly in the hallway.
在走廊上要慢慢走
Yamada?!
山田？
Don't run!
不要用跑的
Hey, Yamada…
山田同学，听我说
She's your guest, isn't--
那个人是你带来的…
Akane!
茜
Please stop for a moment.
请你先等一下
The stairs could be dangerous.
在楼梯跑很危险
Stop her from running, okay?
别让她跑来跑去哦
I'm sorry about back there.
刚才真是抱歉
My name…
你第一次…
You said it for the first time!
叫了我的名字
No, I don't think--
不，怎么可能…
It is true! That was definitely the first time!
是真的，肯定是第一次
I mean… you've gone so long without using it
因为你从来没那样叫过我
that I'd developed a theory
“山田其实根本不知道我的名字吧”
that you didn't even know my name!
我还这么想过呢
That's ridiculous.
怎么可能？
-Anyway, um… -Yamada's talking to a girl.
-然后… -山田在和女生说话…
About what just happened…
关于刚才的事…
Who's that?
那个人是谁？
It can't be true.
不会吧？
Why's she here?
她干嘛来这里？
It's that woman.
就是这女的
Come with me!
你过来这边！
Sorry to pull you into an empty hallway like this.
抱歉哦，带你来没人的地方
I was worried about a knife in the back.
因为我背后的杀气实在太重
Do you really think that?
有这种事吗？
OKAY, NO ONE AROUND…
（好，确定没人…）
I'm sorry for my behavior back there.
刚才真的很抱歉
It was never my intention to make fun of you.
我完全没有戏弄你的意思
I just figured it was another one of Eita's jokes
因为听到瑛太又在开玩笑
and I just--
我就随便配合他一下
Hold on!
等…等等
I'm not angry or anything.
我也没在生气
Let's just drop the subject.
这话题就到此为止吧
You're… not angry?
你…没在生气？
But you were clearly mad just now.
可是刚才很明显是在生气吧
I wasn't! I mean it!
真的没有啦
It was more like…
老实说…
I was a little embarrassed.
是因为觉得有点丢脸…
That's why, I…
我才会忍不住…
HE'S SORRY…
（抱歉…）
had to say something…
说出那种话
Pardon the question,
不好意思
but what was it that embarrassed you?
请问是哪里觉得丢脸？
Let's not go there, okay?
可不可以不要追问这个啊？
So, then…
所以
you really aren't angry?
你真的没有生气吧？
I told you, I'm not--
我就说没有了…
I'm glad.
没生气就好
Shall we go do your shopping then?
那我们去买东西吧
If, by chance…
如果…
If I had taken Eita's joke seriously
假如我把瑛太的玩笑当真
and said that I would date you…
开口说要跟山田交往
If I had done that…
如果我真的这么说
what would you…
山田你…
have done?
会怎么做？
J… Just kidding!
开…开玩笑啦
There are some girls who might react that way,
有些人真的会像这样当真
so it's best not to make jokes about people's love lives!
最好别拿恋爱话题开玩笑哦
Is that clear?
懂了吗？
-Yes. -Okay, then let's go!
-是的… -好，那我们走吧
I must be losing my mind.
我昏头了，真的昏头了
But if you had,
如果真是那样
I think that would be…
我会觉得…
a real honor.
非常光荣
It's just that for a boring guy like me,
但是对我这种无聊家伙来说
someone like you is an unattainable flower,
茜是个高不可攀的对象
so I'd never given it much thought.
所以我没怎么想过那种事
Yamada!
山田
Huh? Do you mean that?
你是说认真的吗？
THAT'S A FUNNY THING TO SAY…
（听起来是有点好笑啦…）
Yeah.
是的
That's how you think of me?
你是那样看我啊？
So what do you need to buy, again?
是要买什么？
Hold on, wait for me!
等等啦
A crepe, a cheese dog,
可丽饼、芝士热狗
takoyaki, and soup.
章鱼烧和猪肉味噌汤
Also, you're more interesting than you think.
话说山田你其实很有趣哦
Really?
真的吗？
Please Yamada, you have to enter the contest this year!
山田，今年你一定要参加校草选拔
No, I really can't.
不，我真的不想
Don't be so hesitant.
别那么说啦，拜托你了
Just look! In the hall!
你看一下教室外面！
-See? -No way.
-对吧？ -我不要
Please! This is our last chance!
求求你，已经是最后一年了啊
We want to make our last school festival the best it can be!
我们想在最后留下最美好的回忆
Yeah, please!
就是说啊，是最后一次了
A handsome face comes with worries, huh?
看来长得太帅也是个困扰
Plus, he's good at video games too.
而且又很会打游戏
-It's like a cheat code. -Come on!
-简直开外挂 -求你了
Shouldn't we put a stop to this?
差不多该阻止了吧
ONE DAY UNTIL THE TOSEI FESTIVAL
（距离东成祭还剩一天）
It can't be helped.
真是没辙
Okay, I'm in!
我参加
Okamoto, you can't just--
冈本同学，你为何自作主张？
Leave it to me, okay?
放心交给我吧
THE DAY OF THE FESTIVAL
（当天）
And now, the moment you've all been waiting for!
终于到重头戏了
After two years of refusing,
轮到连续两年拒绝参加校草选拔
a certain boy is finally going to appear!
那个男人要登场啦！
TOSEI FESTIVAL MR. ACADEMY CONTEST
（东成祭校草选拔）
Entry number six…
参赛编号6号
From year 3, class A…
三年A班
Akito Yamada
山田秋斗
…'s replacement…
现在要替换选手
Pinch hitter, Okamoto.
欢迎代打，冈本同学
Play ball!
开赛！
TOSEI FESTIVAL MR. ACADEMY CONTEST
（东成祭校草选拔）
Where's Yamada?
山田学长呢？
Off the stage, Okamoto!
冈本，你给我滚！
No one called for you!
没人叫你来！
Yes, my favorite foods are hamburgers and French fries.
是的，我喜欢汉堡和薯条
My least favorite thing is hidden shooters in video games.
讨厌蹲点的散弹枪玩家
That's me, Takeaki Okamoto!
我是冈本武明
Thanks for your votes!
请多指教啦
Looking good, Okamoto!
干得好！冈本！
Good luck, Okamoto!
加油啊！冈本学长！
-What are you saying? -Where's Yamada?
你们在说什么？让山田学长上来啦
You're a brave man, Okamoto!
男子汉冈本！
Do it for Yamada!
连山田的份也一起嗨吧！
What was that about hidden shooters?
蹲点是什么啦！
Everyone, please obey the rules for cheering!
声援时请守规矩
You should treat him to a hamburger later on.
你晚点至少要请他吃个汉堡哦
Right.
也是
Give your brother some too.
也给哥哥吃一点
Come on, your brother is hungry!
哥哥我肚子饿了
Even one bite will do!
吃一口就好
Look, I'm open wide…
来嘛
Gross.
恶心
THERE'S QUITE A COMMOTION OUT THERE
（真是热闹啊）